Guide to the Brendan Gill Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Brendan Gill papers
1862-1999
1940-1998
YCAL MSS 791
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
28.17
(37 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers relating to Brendan Gill, a staff writer at The New Yorker magazine from the late 1930s through the 1990s. In addition to professional correspondence, there are letters between Gill and his wife Anne Barnard and other family members. Writings include materials relating to Gill's shorter works, written for The New Yorker and other magazines, and to several of his books, including two early novels, The Trouble of One House (1950) and The Day the Money Stopped (1957), a memoir, Here at the New Yorker (1975), and biographical works, Tallulah (1972), Lindbergh Alone (1980), and Many Masks (1987). Materials include drafts, proofs, research materials, artwork and photographs relating to works, and clippings (reviews). The collection also contains a considerable amount of personal and family records, including diaries, passports, photograph albums, and scrapbooks.
Gill, Brendan, 1914-1997
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Brendan Gill, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 37 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Brendan Gill (1914-1997)
Born in Hartford, Connecticut, Gill attended the Kingswood-Oxford School before graduating from Yale University in 1936. After graduating, Gill joined the staff of The New Yorker, where he worked for more than 60 years. In addition to his contributions to the magazine, he also wrote film and drama criticism and authored 15 books, including a memoir, Here at the New Yorker (1975), about his years at the magazine. Gill was also an advocate for architectural preservation and the visual arts.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers relating to Brendan Gill, a staff writer at The New Yorker magazine from the late 1930s through the 1990s. In addition to professional correspondence, there are letters between Gill and his wife Anne Barnard, with whom he had several children, and other family members. Writings include materials relating to Gill's shorter works, written for The New Yorker and other magazines, and to several of his books, including two early novels, The Trouble of One House (1950) and The Day the Money Stopped (1957), the memoir, Here at the New Yorker (1975), and biographical works, Tallulah (1972), Lindbergh Alone (1980), and Many Masks (1987). Materials include drafts, proofs, research materials, artwork and photographs relating to works, and clippings (reviews). The collection also contains a considerable amount of personal and family records, including diaries, passports, photograph albums, and scrapbooks.
Arrangement
Files are not arranged in any particular order.
New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; New York (N.Y.) -- Periodicals; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Bankhead, Tallulah, 1902-1968; Barnard, Anne; Gill, Brendan, 1914-1997; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974
- October 2002 Acquisition, 1862-1999; 28.17; (37 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The October 2002 Acquisition contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers. In addition to professional correspondence, there are letters between Gill and his wife Ann Barnard, with whom he had several children, and other family members. Writings include materials relating to Gill's shorter works, written for The New Yorker and other magazines, and to several of his books, including the two early novels, The Trouble on One House (1950) and The Day the Money Stopped (1957), the memoir, Here at the New Yorker (1975), and the biographical works, Tallulah (1972), Lindbergh Alone (1980), and Many Masks (1987). Materials include drafts, proofs, research materials, artwork and photographs relating to works, and clippings (reviews). The acquisition also contains a considerable amount of personal and family records, including diaries, passports, photograph albums, and scrapbooks.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 395.
  Gift of the estate of Brendan Gill, 2002.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 2 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 37 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Letters from Anne Gill to her parents, 1930-1940, undated; 8 (Box 1)
    Includes letters from Brendan Gill
  - Letters from Dr. M. H. Gill and Elizabeth, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Tom Gill, aunt Elizabeth, and others, 1952-1992 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Kate Gill to her parents, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Holly Gill, 1959-1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Family letters, 1938-1996, undated (Box 1)
  - Family memorabilia, 1955-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters to Anne and Brendan Gill, 1935-1998, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Anne and Brendan Gill's 60th anniversary, 1996 June; 2 (Box 1)
  - Family photographs, 1957-1999; 24 (Box 2)
  - Drawing of Brendan Gill, 1957-1996, undated (Box 2)
  - Tallulah Bankhead recordings, undated (Box 2)
  - Here at the New Yorker, artwork, undated (Box 2)
  - Unidentified photograph negative, "Job No. 182724", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Kennedy Center", 1980, undated (Box 3)
  - The New Yorker, page proofs, 1945 April 2
  - Here at the New Yorker, captions, undated (Box 3)
  - "Historical Introduction", 1978, undated (Box 3)
  - "Notes for Here at the New Yorker ", undated (Box 3)
  - Unsorted writings, 1945-1982, undated; 11 (Box 3)
  - "Albert Memorial", undated (Box 3)
  - Notes for articles and books, undated (Box 3)
  - Poems, undated (Box 3)
  - Book reviews, undated (Box 3)
  - Many Masks, undated; 8 (Box 3)
  - Notes for articles and books, undated (Box 3)
  - Letters from Anne Gill to Frank Barnard, 1944-1977, undated; 5 (Box 4)
  - Letters from Anne Gill to her parents, 1936-1938; 4 (Box 4)
  - Name badge, undated (Box 4)
  - Anne Gill's plays, undated; 4 (Box 4)
  - Anne Gill's notebooks, 1968-1999, undated; 6 (Box 4)
  - Sarah Lawrence memorabilia, 1931-1969, undated; 4 (Box 4)
  - "A. B. Gill Story", undated (Box 4)
  - Writings by Anne Gill, undated (Box 4)
  - "Church E. Gates - Great Uncle of Anne Barnard Gill: Army Papers", 1862-1864 (Box 4)
  - Anne Gill manuscript and correspondence, 1992, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Abandoned", undated; 5 (Box 5)
  - "Family Matters", undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - "Ways of Loving", undated (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1962 (Box 5)
  - "The Unheralded Boy", undated (Box 5)
  - 60th anniversary cards to the Gills, 1996 June; 3 (Box 6)
  - Condolence cards sent to Anne Gill, 1997-1998; 6 (Box 6)
  - Anne Barnard Gill funeral program, 1999 December 22 (Box 6)
  - Norfolk Library memorial program, 1998 January 3 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Emma Bowen, 1963-1965, undated (Box 6)
  - Directions with map, undated (Box 6)
  - Family trip to Europe, ephemera, 1957-1958, undated (Box 6)
  - Artwork, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6)
  - The New Yorker, cover, 1970 May 23 (Box 6)
  - Family memorabilia, 1994 July 4 (Box 6)
  - "The Morrows", undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Unsorted writings, 1968-1984, undated; 4 (Box 6)
  - Cole, Chapter 1, undated (Box 6)
  - Unsorted writings, 1959-1984; 4 (Box 7)
  - Here at the New Yorker, typescripts, 1978, undated; 6 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 7)
  - Here at the New Yorker, notebooks, undated; 4 (Box 7)
  - Chain link purse, undated (Box 8)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 8)
  - Unsorted writings, 1915-1973, undated; 14 (Box 8)
  - Photographs for books, 1901-1976, undated; 2 (Box 8)
  - Financial material, 1928-1953 (Box 8)
  - CAL letters pre-1930, 1920-1939 (Box 8)
  - Unsorted writings, 1931-1997, undated; 27 (Box 9)
  - Unsorted writings, 1950-1971, undated; 7 (Box 10)
  - Bio, undated (Box 10)
  - Reviews of Gill's work, articles, 1970-1989, undated; 19 (Box 10)
  - Memos, 1925-1991; 7 (Box 10)
  - Appearances, 1975-1989; 2 (Box 10)
  - Mentioned, 1980-1988 (Box 10)
  - "On Architecture, Historic Preservation, Quoted, Appearances, Panel Member", 1970-1990 (Box 10)
  - Clippings about or related to Gill, 1971-1990; 12 (Box 10)
  - Various & sundry, 1971-1994, undated (Box 10)
  - Tallulah, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - "Family Matters", undated; 6 (Box 11)
  - The Day the Money Stopped, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - "The Laurel Tree", undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Unsorted writings, 1949-1957, undated; 5 (Box 11)
  - Lindbergh Alone, responses, 1971-1978, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Unsorted writings, undated (Box 12)
  - Stanford White material, 1883-1906, undated; 14 (Box 12)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 12)
  - Research material re. architecture, 1973-1981 (Box 12)
  - Anne Gill's diaries, 1932-1999; 17 (Box 13)
  - Clippings re Gill and his work, 1968-1990; 8 (Box 14)
  - Many Masks, undated; 2 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks, undated (Box 14)
  - "Naturally One Wants to be a Star", undated (Box 14)
  - The Day the Money Stopped, undated (Box 14)
  - "Family Matters", undated (Box 14)
  - "La Belle", undated (Box 14)
  - "The Unheralded Boy", undated (Box 14)
  - Family photograph album, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Magazines featuring work by Gill, 1972-1995; 18 (Box 15)
  - Anne Gill's desk calendars, 1974-1988; 2 (Box 15)
  - Papers relating to "Cole", 1971, undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - Talk by Gill, 1976 (Box 16)
  - "U.S. Custom House on Bowling Green", 1976 (Box 16)
  - Tallulah, undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - "Meeting Mr. Ives", undated (Box 16)
  - The Day the Money Stopped, 1957-1958; 2 (Box 16)
  - New Yorker articles, proofs, 1990 (Box 16)
  - Lindbergh Alone, production material, 1977; 2 (Box 16)
  - Dorothy Parker, undated (Box 16)
  - "The Malcontents", undated (Box 16)
  - "The Laurel Tree", undated (Box 16)
  - The Abandoned ( The Trouble with One House ), undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - "Stanford White", undated; 3 (Box 16)
  - Notes relating to Brendan Gill's memories of Elizabeth, undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - Awards and presentations, 1986-1995, undated (Box 16)
  - Family photographs, 1938-1998, undated; 15 (Box 17)
  - Financial and business papers, 1973-1982; 9 (Box 18)
  - Century Association material, 1948-1973 (Box 18)
  - Victorian Society material, 1973 March (Box 18)
  - The Municipal Art Society, 1972-1980, undated (Box 18)
  - "Behind the Lines," script for T.V., 1973 November (Box 18)
  - Clippings and reviews, undated (Box 18)
  - Victor Gallancz, 1956 (Box 18)
  - Clippings, 1957-1990, undated; 2 (Box 18)
  - Salzburg seminar material, 1974-1980, undated (Box 18)
  - The Whitney Museum material, 1978-1982 (Box 18)
  - Broadcasted presentations, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Lindbergh Alone, 1976, undated (Box 18)
  - "Happy Times", 1973, undated (Box 18)
  - Landmarks Conservancy material, 1972-1982 (Box 18)
  - "Wooings", 1946-1980 (Box 18)
  - Letters to Brendan Gill, 1943-1996, undated; 13 (Box 18)
  - Gill's responses to letters, 1959-1989; 3 (Box 18)
  - Meaningful checks, 1945-1951 (Box 18)
  - Thank you letters to Brendan Gill, 1977-1981, undated (Box 19)
  - Lindbergh Alone, undated (Box 19)
  - Mobile broadcast commentary, 1979-1980; 3 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1978-1981, undated; 4 (Box 19)
  - Clippings re. architectural preservation, 1974-1979 (Box 19)
  - Architectural preservation material, 1973-1981; 2 (Box 19)
  - Letters to Gill, 1975-1981; 4 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1976-1981; 2 (Box 19)
  - Tallulah, excerpts, undated (Box 19)
  - Photographs for books, undated (Box 19)
  - Salzburg seminar material, undated (Box 19)
  - "Fat Girl," screenplay, undated (Box 20)
  - "Family Matters", undated (Box 20)
  - "Laurel Tree", undated (Box 20)
  - Photographs of Ireland, undated (Box 20)
  - Post-war architecture, undated (Box 20)
  - War with Truman (CIA), undated (Box 20)
  - Travel, post-war, undated (Box 20)
  - Colorado Springs, undated (Box 20)
  - Som., undated (Box 20)
  - The Trouble of One House, reviews, 1950
  - The Trouble of One House, manuscript, undated (Box 20)
  - "Edited Copy", undated (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous material, undated (Box 20)
  - Edited copy of Tallulah, undated; 3 (Box 20)
  - Letters to Lucy Gates, the grandmother of Anne Barnard Gill, 1862-1865; 3 (Box 21)
  - Letters from Frank Edward Barnard, 1946-1980; 5 (Box 21)
  - Letters to Arthur Knox re: Henry James, 1941-1957, undated; 2 (Box 21)
  - Anne Gill's family photographs, 1918, undated (Box 21)
  - Letters to Anne Barnard Gill and Frank Edward Barnard re: Death of Madeline Wemple Barnard, 1946-1948, undated; 4 (Box 21)
  - Letters from Brendan Gill to Frank Edward Barnard, 1948-1960 (Box 21)
  - Anne Barnard letters from Smith, 1934-1936 (Box 21)
  - Letters from Anne Gill to and from her mother, 1945, undated (Box 21)
  - Letters to Madelaine Wemple Barnard, 1914-1915, undated (Box 21)
  - Notebooks, diaries, calendars, 1942-1984, undated; 15 (Box 22)
  - Passports, 1955-1985; 9 (Box 22)
  - Skull and Bones album, 1936 (Box 22)
  - Here at the New Yorker, undated; 7 (Box 23)
  - "Fat Girl", 1970; 2 (Box 23)
  - Unsorted writings, 1979, undated; 18 (Box 23)
  - Reviews, undated (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous material, undated (Box 23)
  - Unsorted writings, undated (Box 24)
  - Here at the New Yorker, artwork, undated; 6 (Box 24)
  - Barry, undated (Box 23)
  - "Articles, Photo (T.H.E.), Biography, Educational", 1921-1938, undated (Box 24)
  - "The Malcontents", undated (Box 24)
  - The Trouble of One House, undated (Box 24)
  - Letters from Anne Gill and Brendan Gill, 1950-1996, undated (Box 24)
  - Letters from Brendan Gill to Frank Barnard, 1951-1977, undated (Box 24)
  - Letters from Brendan Gill to Anne Gill, 1937-1995 (Box 24)
  - Brendan Gill's diary (photocopy), 1941-1943 (Box 24)
  - Anne Gill's diary, 1954 (photocopy), 1916, 1954 (Box 24)
  - Unsorted writings, undated; 5 (Box 25)
  - The Trouble of One House, page proofs, undated
  - Lindbergh Alone, photographs, undated (Box 25)
  - Philip Barry original material, 1921-1949, undated; 2 (Box 26)
  - Photograph of Cole Porter, 1971 (Box 26)
  - Magazines featuring Gill's work, 1975-1994; 4 (Box 25)
  - Tributes, honors, obituaries, 1978-1998, undated; 12 (Box 26)
  - Joseph Campbell material, 1989, undated (Box 27)
  - New York Times, 1998 (Box 27)
  - Philip Barry original material, undated (Box 27)
  - New Yorker photographs and cartoons, undated (Box 27)
  - Mounted photograph with notes, undated (Box 27)
  - New Yorker, 1980-1981; 2 (Box 27)
  - Reporter at Large, 1981 September 28 (Box 27)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 27)
  - New York Times, 1997 December; 3 (Box 28 (Oversize))
  - Framed material, undated (Box 29 (Oversize))
  - Honorary membership, The American Institute of Architects, 1978 (Box 29 (Oversize))
  - Here at the New Yorker, cover art, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - Early land records of the Gill house, 1901-1978 (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - Description of Golf Course Creation for Placemats designed by Rosemary Gill, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - The Saturday Evening Post, 1941 August 9 (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - Articles about Gill, 1997-1998 (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - Framed material, 1993, undated (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - Photograph album, undated (Box 31 (Oversize))
  - Photograph album, "The Gills, Norfolk, CT", 1982 (Box 31 (Oversize))
  - Photograph album, "The Gills", 1980 (Box 32 (Oversize))
  - Photograph album, "The Gills, Norfolk, CT", 1985 (Box 32 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1956, undated (Box 33 (Oversize))
  - Philip Barry original material, 1957, undated (Box 34 (Oversize))
  - Paintings and photographs, undated; 3 (Box 34 (Oversize))
  - Photograph, "Return from Wedding", 1929 (Box 34 (Oversize))
  - The New Yorker, page proofs, 1945 April 2 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Unsorted writings, 1945-1982, undated (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Notes for Gill's articles and books, undated (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Sarah Lawrence memorabilia, 1931-1969, undated (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Unsorted writings, 1959-1984 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Photographs for books, 1901-1976, undated (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Unsorted writings, 1931-1997, undated (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Reviews of Gill's work, articles, 1970-1989 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Memos, 1925-1991 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Appearances, 1987-1989 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - "On Architecture, Historic Preservation, Quoted, Appearances, Panel Member", 1970-1990 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Clippings about or related to Gill, 1971-1990 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Tallulah, 1972-1973 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Unsorted writings, 1949-1957, undated; 2 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Stanford White original material, 1883-1906, undated (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Clippings re. Gill and his work, 1968-1990 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - The Day the Money Stopped, 1957-1958 (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Financial and business papers, 1973-1982 (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Clippings, 1957-1990, undated (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Letters to Gill, 1975-1996, undated (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Clippings re: architectural preservation, 1974-1979 (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Letters to Gill, 1975-1981 (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - The Trouble of One House, reviews, 1950 (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Tallulah, corrected, undated (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - The Trouble of One House, page proofs, undated (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Tributes, honors, obituaries, 1978-1998; 2 (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - Tallulah Bankhead, undated; 1; 00:04:50; Static and a high amount of hum can be heard on the audiotape reel. Clicks and pops can also be heard. (Box 37, Item barcode 39002091243296)
    Contents of the audiotape reel are listed below.
    1. Excerpt from "The Little Foxes" with Eugenia Rawls
    2. "Bye Bye Blackbird"
  - Meeting with Mr. Ives, 1975 August 24; 1; 01:16:10; A high amount of buzz can be heard on the audiotape reel. (Box 37, Item barcode 39002091243304)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult access services for further information.
  - Untitled, undated; 1; 00:31:16 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002091243312)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "The Gill Family at the Geraghty's in Westport, Conn." (film), 1951 Summer (Box 37)
  - "Gill-Dufallo Version (Very Rare)", undated; 1; 00:32:29 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002091243320)
  - Untitled, undated; 1; 00:11:01 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002091243338)
  - "Wasteland", B. Gill and Laurentians, tape sent to A. Gill from C. DeCarlo, 1978 October; 1; 00:33:38 (Box 37, Item barcode 39002091243346)
    A letter sent along with the audiocassette, dated February 28, 1998, reads: Dear Anne, By now you must have read a great number of tributes to Brendan and offers of condolence...all of them deserved. I am not remiss in not being part of that outpouring, rather I decided to wait until the initial shock was past and some measure of peace was yours. Both you and Brendan are among the fondest memories we have of our days and nights at Sarah Lawrence. To put it bluntly having the two of you about was one of the few positive aspects of my having to deal with those irksome neighbors, whom I often thought considered the college a kind of evil empire. Your friendliness and upbeat view of things was so welcome! A chance meeting of Brendan on the street or in a New York club was always such a sudden pleasure. To me his signature was that mischievous grin astride an outgoing enthusiasm. In that regard his willingness to substitute for me, on very short notice, in a performance of Anthony Burgess's musical setting of Eliot's Wasteland was typical of his generosity. That evening someone made a recording of the reading and I want you to have it. The fidelity is not the greatest but Brendan comes through just fine. I hope you and all your kids are well and that the days ahead will be good ones. Cordially, Charles.